<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon preached upon the death of Mr. Nathaniel Oldfield who deceased Decemb. 31, 1696, ætat. 32 : with some account of his exemplary character / by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16971941</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16971941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105563</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105563)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon preached upon the death of Mr. Nathaniel Oldfield who deceased Decemb. 31, 1696, ætat. 32 : with some account of his exemplary character / by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 84, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Astwood for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within mourning border.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: preliminary p. [16] and [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and cropped with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oldfield, Nathaniel, 1664?-1696.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XIII, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:1"/>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon, PREACHED Upon the DEATH of The Reverend Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Oldfield:</hi> Who Deceaſed <hi>Decemb.</hi> 31. 1696. <hi>Aetat.</hi> 32. With ſome Account of his Exemplary Character.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Aſtwood</hi> for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:2"/>
            <head>TO <hi>His Worthy Friend and Brother, Mr.</hi> Joſhua Oldfield.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Honour which it pleaſed God to beſtow on <hi>Your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Brother,</hi> to be ſo much a Bleſſing, and Beloved, while Living, ought to qualifie your Sorrow for his Death; and make you the more ſoftly to lament your Loſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. If the reading of this Sermon do any way renew your Grief, you muſt thank your ſelf, and thoſe who join'd with you, in deſiring to have it publiſhed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:3"/>
            <p>'TWAS his <hi>Serious Godlineſs,</hi> that made him ſo valuable, and in ſome reſpects, <hi>You</hi> and <hi>I</hi> are more obliged than others, to <hi>Follow his Faith,</hi> or Chriſtian Piety; (in
<note place="bottom">* 2 Tim. I. 5. Chap. IV. 6.</note> that ſenſe you know the word is ſometimes uſed.) The Integrity of his Heart towards God, joyn'd with a true Zeal for his Glory, qualified him for great Service as a Miniſter.</p>
            <p>WILL you ſuffer me to mind <hi>my Self</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> (who I am perſwaded, need it leſs than I do) that it was his ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous Care and Concern about the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>his own Soul,</hi> that made him ſo Diligent and Succeſsfull for <hi>the Souls of others.</hi> He had very much Help herein, by the frequent and Attentive Peruſal of the cloſe
<pb facs="tcp:105563:3"/>Warnings and Directions given Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in
<note place="bottom">* <hi>Mr.</hi> B's. Gildas Selvianus, <hi>The Reformed Paſtor</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chap. 1. §. 9. Chap. V. §. 5, 6, 7,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>The Reformed Paſtor,</hi> 
               <q>To take heed, leſt we be Preachers and no Chriſtians, dedicated to the Altar as God's Prieſts, and not ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by dedication to Chriſt as his Diſciples, and ſo worſhip an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God, and preach an unknown Saviour, an unknown Spirit, an unknown ſtate of Holineſs, and Communion with God, and a Glory that is unknown, and like to he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known for ever.—If we ſoundly believe, and are affected with the Truth we ſtudy and preach, we ſhall preach it more heartily. Experience will direct us to the fitteſt Subjects, and furniſh us with Matter, and quicken us to ſet it home. Whereas
<pb facs="tcp:105563:4"/>he is like to be but an Heartleſs Preacher, who is a Stranger to that Chriſt and Grace, he preacheth of to others. And ſo if he do not firſt preach to himſelf, what he teacheth them; for if our own Hearts be cold, our Preaching will be ſo: And if we have but an affected Fervency, we cann't expect a Bleſſing ſhould attend it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THERE are many Paſſages in that Book of the like Tendency, which we can hardly read without Fear and Trembling; ſome of 'em, as I remember, he own'd did moſt deeply affect his Soul, and I have ſometimes thought, they had ſome good impreſſion on mine. I deſire to be more under the Awe and Influence of ſuch Conſiderations. It may be the Recital of a few more
<pb facs="tcp:105563:4"/>of 'em, may be of uſe to ſome of the Younger Miniſters; tho' I know your Character ſo well, that I do not add them for your ſake, but my own, and others. As Face anſwers to Face in a Glaſs, ſo doth the Heart of Man one to another: What was of uſe to him and me, may reach more.</p>
            <p>
               <q>HOW many have preach'd Chriſt, and periſht for want of a ſaving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in him? Many may be now in <hi>Hell,</hi> who have told their Hearers of the Torments of <hi>Hell,</hi> and warn'd them to avoid it. Who have preach'd of the Wrath of God againſt ſinners, and are now feeling of it. O what ſadder Caſe can there be in the World, than for a Man whoſe Buſineſs and Calling it was to proclaim <hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and help others to obtain it,
<pb facs="tcp:105563:5"/>yet after all, himſelf to be ſhut out! That we ſhould have ſo many Books in our Libraries, that tell us the way to <hi>Heaven,</hi> that we ſhould ſpend ſo much time in reading thoſe Books, and ſtudying the Doctrine of Eternal Life, and after all to miſs of it! That we ſhould preach ſo many Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Eternal Salvation, and yet fall ſhort of it: And this becauſe we preached of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but neglected him; of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> but reſiſted him; of <hi>Faith,</hi> but did not heartily believe; of <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Converſion,</hi> but continued in a ſtate of Sin; of <hi>an Heavenly Heart and Life,</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained Carnal and Earthly our ſelves. Do we not know, that <hi>God is no Reſpecter of Perſons,</hi> and that an Holy Calling will never ſave an Unholy Man? That the Preachers
<pb facs="tcp:105563:5"/>of the Goſpel, muſt be judged by the Goſpel; ſtand at the ſame Bar, be ſentenc'd on the ſame Terms, and dealt with as ſeverely as other Men? — It is a fearful thing to be an unſanctified Profeſſor, but much more ſo to be <hi>an Unholy Preacher.</hi> When we open our Bibles, ſhould we not tremble, leſt we read our own Condemnation? When we pen our Sermons, little do we think we are drawing up Indictments againſt our own Souls: When we are arguing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, that we are but aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our own: When we magnifie the Riches of Chriſt, and his Grace, and declare it to others, we publiſh our own Iniquity in rejecting him, and our own Miſery in being Strangers to him. <hi>O Miſerable Life!</hi> that a Man ſhould ſtudy, and preach from
<pb facs="tcp:105563:6"/>year to year againſt himſelf, and ſpend his dayes in a Courſe of Self-condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. — What aggravated Miſery will it be, to periſh in the midſt of Plenty, to famiſh with the Bread of Life in our Hands, while we offer it to others, and urge them to receive it, but we our ſelves will not:</q>
            </p>
            <p>NEXT to His Piety, or as a part of it, his <hi>Peaceableneſs</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> in oppoſition to Bitterneſs, and Dividing Zeal, and a Narrow Spirit, was very Commendable and Exemplary. He could unite with all Chriſtians in Things Neceſſary, and was not for making more Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals and Neceſſaries than Chriſt hath made; or for other Terms of Church-Communion, than the Terms of our Common Chriſtianity: And therefore
<pb facs="tcp:105563:6"/>was ready to receive All, whom he believ'd Christ would receive. He was of <hi>one Church</hi> with All thoſe, whom he hop'd to meet in Heaven. Endeavouring to hold the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace, becauſe he acknowledged that there is but <hi>One Body, one Spirit, one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, one Hope, one Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> (and conſequently but one Holy Table,) <hi>one God and Father of all,</hi> from whom, and by whom, and for whom are all Things.</p>
            <p>'TIS from this Principle, as eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Piety, Learning, and Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men of all Perſwaſions, that I cannot be unaffected at the Death of the Reverend Dr. <hi>Horneck,</hi> of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> this Week: His Devotion, Zeal and Diligence in Preaching, Writing,
<pb facs="tcp:105563:7"/>and otherways endeavouring to do good to the Souls of Men, makes him to be deſervedly and generally lamented; tho' I had no particular Acquaintance with him, I reckon my ſelf bound to value and love every Man, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to promote Reformation, and Practical Religion, and ſpends his Time, as he did, to help to make the World better. I Rejoice in the <hi>Gifts,</hi> and <hi>Graces,</hi> and <hi>Succeſs</hi> of All the Servants of Chriſt, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Denomination.</hi> Yea, I will Eſteem and Love Them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will Own and Love me or no.</p>
            <p>THIS Charitable Spirit, (let who will call ſuch <hi>Moderation</hi> Lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,) with ſerious Diligence to pleaſe God, and do what Service we can in
<pb facs="tcp:105563:7"/>our Several Places, will be accepted with God, and yield us Comfort, liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dying. And will, I doubt not, be better thought of hereafter, when the little Names of Diſtinction and Matters of Diſpute, that now divide Chriſtians and Proteſtants, ſhall be forgotten. As to all the Opinions and Cenſures of Men, while we endeavour to do our Duty, we ought to be firmly perſwaded, that every Man's <hi>Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> is as much at the Diſpoſal of God, and under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Providence, as his <hi>Eſtate</hi> or <hi>Health,</hi> or <hi>Life;</hi> and accordingly we ought to truſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> By what I already know of you, I do not queſtion your Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with me in theſe things. I hope I ſhall know you better, by a nearer
<pb facs="tcp:105563:8"/>and more intimate Acquaintance, if it ſhall pleaſe God to Direct and Guide you, to comply with the Invitation you have (by a unanimous and ſpeedy Choice) to ſucceeed your Brother. However that may be, I beg of God to ſanctifie this Providence to you, to the Congregation, and to all his ſurviving Friends and Acquaintance: May I have Wiſdom, duely to improve it! I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>Febr. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1696/7.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Brother and Servant, <hi>John Shower.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:8"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere will be ſpeedily Publiſh'd a Funeral Sermon, on the Death of Mr. <hi>T. Heaſy,</hi> an Hopeful Student, Aged 19. With Serious Counſel to Young Students, and Candidates for the Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſome Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations on Several Subjects, Collected out of the Papers he left.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:9"/>
            <head>BOOKS Written by the ſame Author, and Sold by <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WInter Meditations: <hi>Or a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concerning Froſt, and Snow, and Winds,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the Wonders of God therein.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Thankſgiving Sermon.</hi> April <hi>the</hi> 16th. 1696. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Account of the Life of Mr.</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gearing. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe of Tempting Chriſt.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe of Family Religion, in three Letters.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105563:9"/>
            <head>A Funeral Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. 13.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Remember them who have the Rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you the Word of God; whoſe Faith fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, conſidering the End of their Converſation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Suitableneſs of this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the preſent Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to the Mournful Occaſion of it, is ſufficiently apparent. The Direction here given, concerning the Peoples Duty, with reſpect to their Miniſters, is entire, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105563:10"/>may be underſtood without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Context. One would think it very eaſie to determine, of what <hi>Miniſters</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks, whether ſuch as were yet <hi>alive,</hi> or ſuch as were <hi>dead;</hi> did not our Tranſlation favour their Opinion, who would make the Original Word a Participle, rather than a Subſtantive, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;) contrary to the more general Senſe of moſt Learned Interpreters and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, who read the Words thus, <hi>Be mindful of your Guides,</hi> or <hi>Rulers, and remember them who <hi>have had</hi> the Rule over you; i. e.</hi> who have been, and were your Spiritual Guides. That 'tis of <hi>theſe</hi> he ſpeaks, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by what follows; <hi>Who have ſpoken to you the Word of God;</hi> or have been your Inſtructors in the Faith; and who have kept the Faith, and finiſhed their Courſe: For he advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them <hi>to follow their Faith,</hi> and to conſider the happy <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Exit of their Converſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS to the Duties unto <hi>Deceaſed Miniſters</hi> here mention'd, it cannot
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105563:10"/>be denyed, but they are applicable in part to other Good Men, departed this Life: For when private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians dye in the Lord, we are not to forget them, and are obliged to imitate their Faith and Patience; and to that end, to conſider their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in <hi>this</hi> World, and how they got ſafe into <hi>another.</hi> But the Apoſtle ſpeaks here of their <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and ſuch of their Spiritual Guides as were departed this Life. With reſpect to theſe, we have <hi>two things</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Account that he gives of them, as to their <hi>Perſons. Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Duty</hi> of ſurviving Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians towards them, after their Death.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>FIRST,</hi> As to their <hi>Perſons,</hi> the Apoſtle gives us an account of them in four Things. 1. As to their <hi>Name,</hi> They are Guides and <hi>Rulers,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2. They have <hi>ſpoken to you the Word of God,</hi> have been <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Everlaſting Goſpel. 3. He te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies <hi>their Exemplary Faith,</hi> propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105563:11"/>them as Patterns. 4. Their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance</hi> in Faith and Holineſs to the laſt; <hi>Conſidering the End of their Converſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. HAVING thus deſcribed their <hi>Perſons,</hi> he mentions <hi>three Duties</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. 1. To <hi>Remember them.</hi> 2. To <hi>Follow their Faith.</hi> 3. As a Motive and a Means thereto, to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their Converſation,</hi> and the happy <hi>End</hi> of it; <hi>Remember them who have had,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall firſt explain theſe ſeveral Particulars in the Text, in the order mentioned; and then Apply my Diſcourſe to the Solemn Occaſion of this Aſſembly, <hi>viz.</hi> the Breach which God hath made amongſt you, by the Death of <hi>my Reverend and worthy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>FIRST,</hi> As to <hi>the Perſons</hi> here deſcribed: They are called <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Guides,</hi> for ſo the Original Word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports; ſuch as have the Guidance and Inſtruction of others, by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or Office. It is ſometimes uſed for Civil Rulers, ſometimes for Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical; and for the General of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105563:11"/>for the Captain of a Regiment, for the Governour of a Town, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a Principal Perſon amongſt others, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.22.</p>
            <p>THE Sacred Writers make uſe of this Word, for ſuch as were eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to feed the Flock of Chriſt, and had the Over ſight of Particular Churches, ſo <hi>Ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves; for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give an account;</hi> the like 24. ver. <hi>Salute all them that have the Rule over you, and all the Saints;</hi> 'tis doubted, whether St. <hi>James,</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was then alive; and more, whether the Apoſtle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects this Epiſtle to all the Churches in <hi>Judea,</hi> or only to the Converted <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> I ſhall not go about to decide it. 'Tis plain, that theſe Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, theſe Warchmen are the ſame, who in the Text had ſpoken the Word of God, or preach'd the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>TO this purpoſe we find that <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Romanus,</hi> who is the moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Writer of the Chriſtian Church,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105563:12"/>next the Apoſtles, (the ſame <hi>Clemens</hi> who is mentioned by the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3.) in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> uſeth this very word very frequently for
<note place="bottom">* <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 73. St. <hi>Clemens Rom.</hi> Epiſt. 1. ad <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4to. Edit. <hi>Patr. Junij Oxon.</hi> 1633.</note> Goſpel Miniſters, Biſhops, ſuch as preach'd the Word of God, and were over 'em in the Lord, and ſeveral of them in one Church, making uſe ſometimes of the one Name, ſometimes of the other,</p>
            <p>OUR Bleſſed Saviour is called the Head, the Husband, the Shepherd, the Lord of his Church, which imports <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;</hi> and the Church is his Body, his Spouſe, his Flock, his Family and Houſhold; and his Miniſters are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Rulers of his Houſhold, Mat.</hi> 24.45. When he was about to leave the World, he declared that all Power in Heaven and Earth was committed to him, and commiſſioned his Apoſtles to make Diſciples by baptizing and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, promiſing his preſence with them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105563:12"/>therein <hi>to the end of the World:</hi> And when he aſcended up on high, he gave Gifts to Men, as part of his Dowry, not only Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Evangeliſts, who were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered by Miracles as a Divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, to prove their Authority to reveal and publiſh the Rule of Faith and Life, but <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> to open and apply the Rule they ſealed and delivered.</p>
            <p>HE hath determined in his Word, that every Church ſhould have a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> one or more; he hath ſtated the Nature of the Miniſterial Office and Power, to proclaim Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins, to turn Men from the power of Satan to God, to edifie the Body of Chriſt, and to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, feed and govern the Churches of Chriſt, to rule as well as teach the Flock, to judge who ſhould be publickly taken into the Church by Baptiſm, or caſt out; to rebuke thoſe that are diſorderly, and ſee that all things be done to the Edification of the Church, to bind over the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105563:13"/>who are <hi>contumacious,</hi> to the Bar of Chriſt, and reject 'em from the Communion of the Church, and to abſolve the penitent, and comfort 'em, and by themſelves, or others, to look after the Poor, and viſit the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He hath deſcribed the Perſons that he would have to be ſuch Officers, by their requiſite Qualifications; he did not appoint a neceſſary Work to be done, and leave it to the wide World who ſhould do it: And that will help to determine, who are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Perſons, that are fitteſt accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt's Deſcription.</p>
            <p>I DISPUTE not, whether there hath not been, and ought not to be, a diſtinction of Powers and Perſons in Eccleſiaſtical Government, or whether an abſolute Equality muſt not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be attended with very ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences; or whether Miniſters do not need Order, and Rule, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment among themſelves, as well as every other Company and Society of Men in the World. But that which I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from this Text, is this, That they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105563:13"/>who <hi>preach</hi> the Goſpel, are to <hi>Guide, Overſee</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> their own Flock, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>THEY are the <hi>Servants of Chriſt</hi> in his Work, and <hi>your Servants for Jeſus ſake.</hi> They pretend not to Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over your Faith, or to be Lords or Owners of the Flock, but to be Helpers of your Joy; by their care the Sheep are to be ſed, guided, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, healed and brought home. They are <hi>Rulers</hi> over Chriſt's Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, but not by ſecular Force and Rigour, not to compel Men to the Faith and Obedience of the Goſpel, otherwiſe than by Truth and Love, by Inſtruction and Perſwaſion, and declaring the Mind of Chriſt in his Word. You are not to obey Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as Civil Magiſtrates, that rule by the Sword, but thankfully receive the Truths they teach, and the Mercies they offer. Our Weapons in the Chriſtian Warfare are not <hi>Carnal,</hi> but <hi>Spiritual,</hi> to Edification, not deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not coercive, but miniſterial: We are to inſtruct and warn, to reprove
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105563:14"/>and exhort with Faithfulneſs and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs, in the Name of Chriſt, and with his Authority, which as it is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing from the Power of a
<note place="bottom">* See Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Paraphraſe and Annotations on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.30. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.7, 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, &amp;c.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, ſo by vertue of the Order and Inſtitution of Chriſt, it is very different from the private Counſel and Admonitions of one Friend to another. The ſame works are not done with the ſame Authority, Efficacy, Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty or Order, by a private hand, as by publick Officers. For in this caſe you are obliged to <hi>Submit your ſelves in the Lord,</hi> to whatever is made known to you to be according to the Will of God, revealed in his Word. 'Tis true, if we exceed our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, you are not to receive us, but if we keep to the Words of Chriſt, he that deſpiſeth our Meſſage, <hi>Deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not Man, but God.</hi> You know how earneſtly the Apoſtle admoniſhes to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>We beſeech you, Brethren, to mind them who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105563:14"/>labour amongſt you, and preſide over you,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the Lord; i. e.</hi> in the things of the Lord, and according to his Order; <hi>and that admoniſh you, and to eſteem them more than exceedingly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in love, for their Work or Office ſake:</hi> And let the Elders who rule well, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>be counted worthy of double Honour,</hi> or Recompence, as the Original Word often ſignifies, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18.</p>
            <p>I MAY be blamed by ſome, for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus much; but there are certain Seaſons, when it is expedient (at leaſt not unfit) for a Man to praiſe the Country or the Family to which he belongs, or the Society to which he is related: And therefore I here take the Liberty to <hi>Magnifie mine Office,</hi> tho' I ſhould <hi>become a Fool in glorying,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. As to the Inſtitution, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and Authority of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, it is <hi>not of Men, or by Man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead,</hi> Gal. 1.1. they received their Miniſtry <hi>from the Lord,</hi> Col. 4.17. he <hi>makes</hi> 'em <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105563:15"/>Acts 20.28. <hi>Timothy</hi> is called the <hi>Servant of the Lord,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24. Miniſters by their Office are as it were his Menial Servants, that approach nearer to his Perſon than others, and are employed in his particular Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They are Stewards over the Houſe and Family of God, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. which is no mean ſtation. They are called <hi>Preſidents, Guides, Rulers, Shepherds, Planters, Husbandmen, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, and the Glory of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the Miniſters of his Spiritual Kingdom, Angels of the Churches, Builders of his Church,</hi> &amp;c. By Baptiſm to initiate Diſciples unto Chriſt, and by the other Sacrament to confirm them, to feed 'em with the ſincere Milk of the Word, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for them in Prayer, to bleſs them in the Name of Chriſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey his Meſſages, Inſtructions, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Comforts to 'em, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Inſtitution and Appointment they could no more do, than a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger can carry a Pardon to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Perſon, which his Prince ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105563:15"/>ſent. <hi>No man taketh the Honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. THEY are deſcribed to be ſuch as <hi>have ſpoken unto you the Word of God.</hi> To feed the Flock, by ſound Doctrine. Serious Study of the Holy Scriptures, and diligent Preaching of the Word, is no little part of the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of a Goſpel-Miniſter. <hi>Simon Peter, loveſt thou me? Feed my Sheep, feed my Lambs.</hi> As Stewards of the Houſhold, they are to provide for the Family; as Shepherds, to feed by Teaching. And it is in great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Mercy to the Souls of Men, that our Bleſſed Lord has appointed ſome Perſons on purpoſe to devote themſelves to this Work; that they may be able to inſtruct the Ignorant, and eſtabliſh the Wavering, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort the Sad, and recover the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlider; to awaken, warn, convince and encourage Others in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Warfare. And whatever ſome pretend, that there is no ſuch need of Preaching <hi>now,</hi> as there was in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105563:16"/>the Infancy of the Church; yet in all Ages, this is the <hi>ordinary Means,</hi> which God hath appointed, and is wont to bleſs, for the Converſion and Salvation of Souls, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. It pleaſeth God now, as well as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching to ſave them that believe.</hi> And it is the Commiſſion of our Saviour for the Miniſterial Office, that <hi>they Preach the Goſpel to every Creature.</hi> And this, not only to plant a Church, but to carry on its growth; it is for <hi>the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> and <hi>for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt.</hi> The Miniſtry of the Goſpel may be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Converts, and Believers, and real Saints, and is ſo, there being ſomething ſtill lacking to their Faith and Comfort. And they had need to be put always in Remembrance of the things they do know, that they may be rooted and eſtabliſhed in the Truth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>IT is wonderful to Obſerve, how our Saviour rather choſe to Convert Men by the Preaching and Miracles
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105563:16"/>of his Apoſtles, than by his own; how he would not fully convert <hi>Paul</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Miniſtry of <hi>Annanias,</hi> tho' he ſpake to him from Heaven himſelf, and reaſoned with him againſt his Perſecution; how he would not fully convert <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Houſhold, without the Miniſtry of <hi>Peter,</hi> tho' he ſent an Angel to direct him to a Teacher, nor would he convert the <hi>Ethiopian Eunuch,</hi> without the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Phillip;</hi> nor the Goaler with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Miniſtery of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> tho' he wrought a Miracle to prepare for his Converſion. Our Lord knew the Neceſſity that the Infants of his Family had of ſuch Nurſes, and he will keep up the Honour of his own Officers, whom he hath appointed for ſuch an End and Uſe.</p>
            <p>HOW much the Welfare of the Church depends upon the Miniſters and Teachers of the Word, and how little the Beauty and Glory of Religion can ever be kept up in the World, if Miniſters do not <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105563:17"/>very eaſily appear, to ſuch as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how Religion has declined and been loſt, by the Ignorance, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, and Negligence of thoſe that ought to have Preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt: And how the Denial or Contempt of the Miniſtry hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way been accompanied with the growth of Atheiſm, Infidelity, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs. How ſolemnly does the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle charge the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Acts 20.28, 30. <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves, and to all the Flock, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers, to feed the Church of God which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood, and to warn every man, leſt they be perverted by falſe Teachers,</hi> &amp;c. And how expreſly to the like purpoſe, are they required to labour with their utmoſt ſtrength in this Work, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.16. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12. They are <hi>To give themſelves continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to Prayer, and the Miniſtry of the Word,</hi> Acts 6.4.</p>
            <p>AND how needful is it that they ſhould do ſo, who are to unfold the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105563:17"/>Mind of God to others; to teach them what they muſt know, believe and do, avoid, and hope for; who have ſo many difficulties to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and ſo often need the Tongue of the Learned, and a good ſhare of Prudence, to ſpeak a Word in Seaſon: To acquaint their Hearers with their ſeveral Maladies and Remedies, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Duties, to hold forth the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Chriſt, ſo as to make him receiv'd and obey'd, admired and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and to be diligent in ſuch Work in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon; mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all, as under an Awe of God, and with ſincere Compaſſion and Love to Souls.</p>
            <p>SUPPOSING <hi>the Word of God</hi> here to be <hi>the Written Word,</hi> I need not enquire curiouſly, how much of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation, or the Written Word, was then extant, when the Apoſtle wrote this Epiſtle, (which is thought to be about the fifty ſeventh, or fifty eighth year of our Bleſſed Lord, while he was a Priſoner at <hi>Rome,</hi> and towards the end of his firſt Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105563:18"/>there.) All the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeems to be then written, ſave the Epiſtles of St. <hi>John,</hi> and his <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> and the Second Epiſtle of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> 'Tis certain, that the whole Word of God in the Holy Scriptures, is to be explained, and applyed by Preaching, and that this is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part of a Miniſters Work. They therefore who pretend to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Office, according to the order of Chriſt, and yet either deſpiſe, or neglect the <hi>Preaching of the Word,</hi> one would think, either do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their Office, or are not faithful to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. ANOTHER Thing concerning theſe Deceaſed Miniſters the Apoſtle mentions, is, their <hi>Exemplary Faith.</hi> They would not have been propoſed as Patterns, with reſpect to <hi>Faith,</hi> if they had not been Famous and Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, as to the Clearneſs of their Minds, and the Soundneſs of their Doctrine. <hi>Follow their Faith.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he means it of ſuch, who as to Knowledg, and firmneſs of Perſwaſion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105563:18"/>concerning the Truths of the Goſpel, and fruitfulneſs in ſuitable Effects, did in Spirit and Practice, ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Believers.</hi> They would not otherwiſe have been named, as fit Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for the People to follow, as to their <hi>Faith.</hi> You find Miniſters are exhorted to <hi>Take heed to their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> 1 Tim. IV. 16. and to continue therein, that they <hi>May ſave themſelves, and them that hear them, and to ſpeak the things that become ſound Doctrine,</hi> 1 Tim. VI. 3. They are to keep the Doctrine of the Goſpel pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt, and to feed the People with the ſincere Milk of the Word. For if the Doctrine, which ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Faith and Holineſs, ſhould be depraved by the Miniſters of the Word, how is it poſſible that true Chriſtianity ſhould ſpread and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or be preſerved and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? What need have we to beg, that God would give and continue ſuch <hi>Paſtors after his own Heart,</hi> as may feed his People with <hi>Good Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> and <hi>Sound <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> They
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105563:19"/>muſt hold faſt the faithful Word that they have been taught, that they may be able, <hi>by ſound Doctrine</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, and convince Gain-ſayers, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6, 9. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.1. Such Speech that cannot be condemned, that he who is of the contrary party may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And how comfortably and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully may they preach to others, who are firmly perſwaded of the Truth of what they ſay; who believe and live the Truths they deliver? This is a great help to Miniſters in their Work, and a great Advantage in order to Succeſs.</p>
            <p>THESE here, whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, were alſo <hi>Exemplary</hi> in all <hi>the Fruits of Faith:</hi> They lived up to the Doctrine they preached, and therein others are exhorted to <hi>follow</hi> them. They repreſented in a Holy Life, the Doctrine they taught, and ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, in whoſe Name they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed it. By Humility and Meekneſs, Moderation and Self-denial, Zeal for the Glory of God, Mortification of Corrupt Affections, Contempt of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105563:19"/>World, Readineſs for the Croſs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion and Patience towards All, Heavenly-mindedneſs, <hi>&amp;c. In all things,</hi> Miniſters <hi>ſhould ſhow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Patterns of good works, and be Examples unto Believers in Word, in Converſation, in Charity, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity,</hi> Tit. II. 2, 7. 1 Tim. IV. 12.</p>
            <p>THIS is the moſt likely Method to have Succeſs: <q>For tho' it may now and then poſſibly fall out, that the Seed of Divine Truth,
<note place="bottom">* Dr. <hi>Spurſtow</hi>'s Medit. on a Debauched Miniſter <hi>Medit.</hi> XX. 8vo.</note> like Corn ſown by a Leprous Hand, may grow up into ſome fruit; yet how ſmall is the <hi>Good,</hi> that is wrought by his Doctrine, in compariſon of the great <hi>Hurt</hi> that is done by the diſſolute Life of ſuch a Miniſter? Is it likely, that he, that in the Pulpit pleads for Honour unto the Perſon of Chriſt, for Obedience to his Commands, and Faith to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in his Promiſes, and when he is out of it, contradicts all that he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105563:20"/>hath ſaid, by a ſenſual practice; is it likely he ſhould ever win many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to Chriſt? Will Men ever hearken to ſuch, who decry Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, and Wantonneſs, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the way to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and yet turn not their own feet from walking therein? will they not ſay, Phyſician, heal thy ſelf? or thou Hypocrite, <hi>Firſt caſt the Beam out of thine own Eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to cast out the Mote that is in thy Brothers Eye.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>HOW can He be a Pattern to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, in thoſe Graces he is a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to? How can he kindle Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affections in the Souls of others, when he feels nothing himſelf? How can he ſpeak of Divine Truth, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Excellency, and Neceſſity, and Importance of it, if he doth not believe, and live, and obey it himſelf? We may as well think, that a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick may teach you the Truth, as well as the Orthodox; and a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick teach you Unity and Peace, as well as a Catholick Peaceable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105563:20"/>or a Man ignorant of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the Grace of God, may teach you that which he knoweth not himſelf; or an Enemy to Piety and Charity, teach you to be Pious and Charitable, as well as any other. The voice of <hi>Jacob</hi> will do little good, if the Hands be the Hands of <hi>Eſau.</hi> They that are unholy, and unexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced as to real Godlineſs, they have <hi>a ſecret Enmity</hi> in their Hearts againſt that Holineſs, which they ſhould daily preach, which is a Clog at their Feet, and a Gag in their Mouths, as to ſome Truths and Duties. They will ſome way or other harden, and embolden others in their Sins, as well as make themſelves, and the Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord contemptable, by ſhewing, that they do not believe what they ſay. How can you think they ſhould lead you in the way of Holineſs, who never walked i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? or guide you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and conduct you in the Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, who are Servants of the World, the Devil, and the Fleſh, againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105563:21"/>whom they muſt Exhort you to Fight.</p>
            <p>HOW dreadful will be the Account and Portion of ſuch Evil Stewards, and Unfaithful Guides, who preach to others, and yet periſh! As the Men that were employed to build the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> yet were not ſaved in it. <hi>He that winneth Souls is wiſe;</hi> but it is he only, that ſhall <hi>do,</hi> as well as <hi>teach</hi> the Commandments, who ſhall be called great in the Kingdom of Heaven, or ever come there. The Judge himſelf hath told us, that many in his Name may have propheſied, and preached, and caſt out Devils, and yet ſhall be diſclaimed, as <hi>Workers of Iniquity.</hi> And it is certainly more eaſie to make <hi>ten</hi> good Sermons, than to practice <hi>one;</hi> and to expoſe and declaim againſt all Sins, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh any.</p>
            <p>HOW terrible is that known paſſage of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> with relation to this? Saying, <q>That he is perſwaded, that <hi>very few</hi> of thoſe who are entruſted with the Goſpel, and Care of Souls,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105563:21"/>are likely to be Saved; and that he apprehends the far greater part will be damned. For this Work, ſaith he, requires a Soul more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; He had need have a thouſand Eyes in his Head, and have them all awake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> How ſevere are the Pſalmiſts Words, and how upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Ungodly Miniſters, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16, 17. <hi>What haſt thou to do, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my Statutes, or that thou ſhouldſt take my Covenant into thy Mouth? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou hateſt Inſtruction, and caſteſt my Words behind thee.</hi> How muſt ſuch a Man be confounded in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt his own Sins, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Damnation againſt himſelf? And with how little Succeſs can he pray for the People of his Charge, when he himſelf is not reconciled to God. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>the Elders of the Church,</hi> when ſick, ſaith the Apoſtle, and the Prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the Sick, but 'tis the ſervent <hi>Prayer of a Righteous Man,</hi> James V. 14, 15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. HE mentions their <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance in Faith and Holineſs,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105563:22"/>'till the happy <hi>End,</hi> and Exit <hi>of their Converſation.</hi> And this he exhorts them to <hi>Conſider,</hi> to review, to reflect upon; and that not tranſiently, but with deep Attention; not once only, but again and again. To conſider what their Carriage and Deportment hath been in publick, and in private; what was their Behaviour in every Relation and Condition, as keeping a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, both towards God and Man; and this not for a ſtart, for a little while, for a few Years only, and then drew back or turned afide: But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>The End of their Converſation.</hi> How they finiſhed their Courſe with Joy. Their Beginning, and Progreſs was commendable, and their latter End was anſwerably good and ſafe, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and happy, either by a natural death, in the Peace of God, or with the Crown of Martyrdom by a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent one.</p>
            <p>I SHALL not need to enquire, how far the Apoſtle may here refer to the Death of the firſt Martyr <hi>Stephen,</hi> and of <hi>James</hi> the Son of <hi>Zebbedee,</hi> who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105563:22"/>both exerciſed their Miniſtty at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and ſuffered Martyrdom <hi>there,</hi> as 'tis thought did the other <hi>James,</hi> the Brother of our Lord, ſeveral years before the date of this Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. LET us conſider what is the Peoples Duty to ſuch their Deceaſed Miniſters and Paſtors. It is threefold. 1. To <hi>Remember</hi> them. 2. To <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> them in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſs.</hi> 3. In order to this, to <hi>Conſider</hi> ſeriouſly, and often <hi>their Converſation,</hi> and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>End</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. REMEMBER your Spiritual Guides, who have had the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Conduct of your Souls, and faithfully diſcharged their Office. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them,</hi> ſo as to be thankful to God for their Gifts and Graces, and for all the Flelp and Aſſiſtance, you had by their Doctrioe and Example, while they lived, and for all the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Grace of God towards them, in enabling them to do or ſuffer his Will, with their Supports, Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105563:23"/>Aſſiſtances, Encouragements, and Victory. <hi>Remember them,</hi> ſo as to bewail your Loſs, and lay to Heart their Removal. Remember how much more you ought to have va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued their Miniſtry, and how much better you might have improved it; (the very thoughts of what you would do, if God would again have tryed you in that kind, might herein be your Help.) Remember what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, what Warnings and Reproofs, what Encouragements and Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you have ever had by their means. Remember with what an Awe of god they were wont to Pray, with what a Zeal for Chriſt, and Love to Souls, they did uſe to Preach; with what humble Condeſcenſion, Meekneſs and Charity, and unblameable Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they lived in this World.</p>
            <p>REMEMBER them in your Thoughts and Affections, and in your Words and Actions; ſo as on all fit Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to expreſs your Love to their Memory. Be ready to ſhew that you do not forget them, by your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105563:23"/>Reſpects and Kindneſs to the Living, for the ſake of the Dead: I mean, the many deſpiſed Widows, and Fatherleſs Children of Worthy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Think often of them, how God honoured them, to bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls to Chriſt, and to build up Others: How ſucceſsfully they mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and comfortably finiſhed their Work. Think <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>where</hi> they now are, what they are delivered from, what they enjoy, how they are employed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Don't be afraid to think often of your Deceaſed Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Friends: 'Tis a plain Duty, and a help to many Duties, to have our Converſation in Heaven with Chriſt, and the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect. To think of our Holy Relations and Acquaintance, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Ministers,</hi> who are got ſafe to Heaven: It may aſſiſt and animate us, in our Spiritual Warfare. And much of the Comfort of the Life of Faith depends upon it. They are part of the Family of Chriſt, to which we are adjoined, if by Faith we are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105563:24"/>united to him, <hi>Heb.</hi> XII. 22, 23. We have no reaſon to believe, that they Forget us whom they have left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; and certainly there is none, why we ſhould Forget them. Let us remember them with Pleaſure, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Love; and ſpeak of them with Reſpect and Gratitude.</p>
            <p>CAN we think with Pleaſure of ſuch a Friend or Miniſter, of ſuch an Acquaintance or Relation, whom we tenderly love, that is many Miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from us, here upon Earth; and ſhall we be unmindful of thoſe who are in Heaven? It ſhould be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placential Thought, to conſider, that ſuch a Father or Grand-father, ſuch a Husband or Wife, ſuch a Child or Brother of yours or mine, are now with Chriſt, in the Boſom of his Love in glory. That ſuch a Miniſter of Chriſt, who was my Spiritual Father, or by whom I was edified, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, or comforted for many Years, hath overcome, and is at Reſt, has fought the good Fight, and finiſhed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105563:24"/>his Courſe. While we are following after, they have attained: While we are in Tears and Conflicts, they are in Joy and Glory: While we are waiting at the door, they are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within the Vail. 'Tis our Duty to <hi>Remember them.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. TO <hi>Follow their Faith,</hi> that is, the Doctrine they preached, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, profeſſed, and obeyed; or their found Doctrine, and Practical Godlineſs. Or their Faith may be conſidered, as regarding Doctrines to be believed and profeſſed, Promiſes to be embraced and depended on, and Precepts to be obeyed. Such <hi>a Faith,</hi> as realized the other World to them, and help'd to crucifie them unto this. Such <hi>a Faith,</hi> as was the Evidence of things unſeen, whereby they were enabled to walk in Self-denyal, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and ſtedfaſt Obedience, 'till they came to the End of their Faith and Hope. In ſhort, we muſt follow them, as holding the Myſtery of Faith in a pure Conſcience, and expreſſing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105563:25"/>the Power of it in a fruitful Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
            <p>YOU ſee, in what it is your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed and Holy Friends, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are to be followed, it is in <hi>their Faith,</hi> and in the Principal Actings and Fruits of it, ſo far as they kept <hi>The Example of Chriſt</hi> in their Eye, and followed him, for no farther does the Apoſtle require it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XI. 1. the Pattern of Chriſt is propos'd for Imitation in all Ages of the Church: We are no leſs obliged to it, than the Apoſtle who prays for the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that the <hi>ſame Mind</hi> might be <hi>in them,</hi> that was <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 11.5. <hi>And therefore have we boldneſs in the day of Judgment,</hi> ſays another Apoſtle, becauſe <hi>We are in the World, as he was in it,</hi> 1 John IV. 17.</p>
            <p>OUR Lord is the only Infallible and Supream Pattern, whom tho' we cannot follow in his Miracles and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and what was peculiar to him as Mediator; yet hath he ſet us <hi>an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> that we ſhould tread in his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105563:25"/>ſteps, in Obedience to his Father, in Zeal for his Glory, in Submiſſion to his Will, in Patience under Suffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He gave us an Example of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Parents, Obedience to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Painfulneſs in Preaching, Frequency in praying, and in going up and down the World doing good, in Forgiving Enemies, in Charity to all Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS to <hi>all other Examples,</hi> tho' there may be ſome things Imitable, there are others, wherein we ſhould be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned not to do the like; as in <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot, David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> &amp;c. Even St. <hi>Peter</hi> was a <hi>Rock,</hi> and an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Apoſtle; but we ſhould ſplit upon that Rock, if we ſhould follow him in all his ways: If we follow him into the High Prieſts Hall, if we imitate him in making bold with Temptation, inſtead of following Chriſt, we may be brought to deny him. Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly cautions us, how far we are to follow his Example, <hi>Phil.</hi> IV. 8. <hi>Finally, my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105563:26"/>Brethren, whatſoever things are honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, of good report; if they have any vertue, any praiſe, think of theſe things, which you have both learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and received, and heard, and ſeen in me, do theſe things, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HOWEVER, granting the Life of Chriſt <hi>only</hi> be a perfect Copy, yet the good Examples of our <hi>Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Fellow-Chriſtians,</hi> are a merciful Help, and Aſſiſtance to us in the way to Heaven. We ſee by their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> that our Duty is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable. That they who dwelt in ſuch Bodies as we, and were ſurrounded with the like Temptations, and had as many Hindrances and Difficulties, and no more, or better Aſſiſtance or Encouragement than we, have yet been enabled to pleaſe and glorifie God, and are got ſafe to Glory. We are not the Forelorn Hope, not the firſt Aſſailors in the Spiritual Warfare, we are not ſet in the Front of the Battle; many of our Fellow Chriſtians
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105563:26"/>have lived and dyed in the Faith, have overcome the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, in that very way, that we are called to do it.</p>
            <p>MANY of our Fellow Soldiers have fought the Good Fight, gained the Victory, and received the Crown. Their Example tells us, that the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Conflicts that we fear, are no other than they have experienced. They complained as much we can, of inward Corruption, and outward Temptation; of an unfaithful World, and a buſie Devil, and a deſperately wicked Heart; and yet by the Grace of God they have Overcome. We have a <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> among our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Friends and Acquaintance, whom we have known and loved, whom we have ſeen and heard, with whom we have convers'd and diſcours'd: And it is a great Encouragement, to conſider we are to follow <hi>Them.</hi> For why ſhould we be diſheartned, as if that were Impobſſile to us, which the Grace of God hath enabled them to do and ſuffer?</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:105563:27"/>
            <p>TIS one great Deſign of God's Gifts, and Graces to <hi>Some,</hi> that they may inſtruct and edifie <hi>Others.</hi> The path of the juſt in this ſenſe, is a ſhining Light: We are to <hi>Shew forth the Word of Life</hi> in our Converſation, that we may direct others in the way: And <hi>by our Zeal,</hi> we are to <hi>provoke many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND when the Precept is exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified into Pattern, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt made legible in the Lives of Chriſtians, we are the more encouraged to obey. This hath more Influence than meer Law, and naked Authority. We find that Examples ſtrangely affect us, and the Lives of Holy Perſons, writ with Truth, and Judgment, and Caution, have a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Advantage to attract our Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. When Charity and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Self-denial and Patience, Piety and Devotion, are characterized in the Practice and Actions of the Saints, they are written as it were with <hi>Light,</hi> notwithſtanding ſome mixture of <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> from Humane Paſſions, and Failings,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105563:27"/>for which in all Men there muſt be Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance. That Holy Examples are apt to affect the Mind more deeply than Holy Laws alone, is evident by the Malice of the Devil, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments againſt the Holy Scriptures, exemplified in the Godly, more than againſt the Scriptures themſelves; they can better bear the Precepts of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Rule, than the imperfect practice of them in a Holy Life. They have burnt Martyrs, that could endure good Books.</p>
            <p>SUCH <hi>Examples</hi> may be of Uſe, both to <hi>Quicken</hi> and <hi>Enoourage</hi> us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. TO quicken and excite our <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> to this purpoſe the Apoſtle makes mention of them, <hi>Chap.</hi> VI. 12. <hi>Be not ſloathful, but be ye followers of them, who by Faith and Patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Promiſes.</hi> To cure the Sloath and Lazineſs of Chriſtians, he ſaith this, and to ſtir them up to Holy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; with this Encouragement in the following Words, that if they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105563:28"/>their Guides in their Faith in Chriſt, they will find him an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, never failing Saviour: For it is added, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to day, and for ever. i.e.</hi> He will certainly receive, forgive, aſſiſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and ſave them, as he did their Deceaſed Guides. If we follow them, we ſhall find the ſame Comfort, and meet with the ſame Reward.</p>
            <p>HOW may the Temper, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Carriage, of ſuch Exemplary Chriſtians, ſhame our Negligence? Their Humility and Zeal, their Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Seriouſneſs, their continual Awe of God, and Apprehenſion of his Eve, their conſtant Watchfulneſs over Hearts, Words and Actions, may be conſidered to humble and ſhame us: When I think how diligently they improved their Talents, how faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fervently they attended their Work, how their Hearts were in it, and how much they did in a little time, and how God was with 'em in abundant Succeſs, it ſhould ſhame and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105563:28"/>quicken me. <q>Do I pray, or preach, or live at that rate of Seriouſneſs, Integrity, Self-denial, and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs to God, as they? Durſt they have indulged themſelves, and pleaſed themſelves, and allowed themſelves the Liberty which I take: Were they guilty of ſuch Omiſſions and Neglects as I am? Am not I more ſlight and formal, ſeldom and heartleſs in Prayer, than they were wont to be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>IF we have the ſame Spirit of Faith, with the Holy Perſons, whoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples we read or hear of, theſe things will quicken and aſſiſt us, for ſo the Apoſtle argues, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> IV. 13. <hi>We hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame ſpirit of Faith, according as it is written, I believed, and therefore have I ſpoken, we alſo believe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpeak.</hi> And if they do not move us, and excite us to follow them, in their Faith and Obedience, it is a ſign that we are not partakers of the ſame Spirit.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105563:29"/>
            <p n="2">2. NOT only as to Duty, but let us conſider 'em for our <hi>Encouragement</hi> and <hi>Comfort.</hi> Whatever Difficulties we may meet with in the Chriſtian Race, the Conſideration of theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples may encourage our Faith, and Patience, and Perſeverance. They found the Sweetneſs of Dependance upon God, and the Succeſs of a Life of Faith, and had gracious Anſwers to Prayer, and ſuitable Help in every time of need: They could ſet to their Seal that God is true, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture true; and never any Word of his, in which they regularly truſted, did ever fail them. And is it no Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, for us to be able to ſay, <hi>Lord, our Fathers truſted in thee, and were delivered; they truſted in thee, and were not aſhamed; they cryed to thee, and thou didſt anſwer them:</hi> 
               <q>They have told us what thou didſt for them: How Good was God, and Faithful, how Wiſe and Gracious! The Word of the Lord is tried, in ſix and in ſeven Troubles they found it true.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105563:29"/>
            <p>AND we that live in the latter Ages of the World, have a greater Cloud of Witneſſes than others; we have the Benefit of the Experience of all the Saints, that have gone before us. They can tell us what they have found, of the falſe Cavils, Slanders and Objections of Unbelief; of the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Diſingenuity of our Carnal Fears, of the Fraud of the Devil's Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, of the certain Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God's Promiſes, and a good Iſſue of all Events, if we wait on the Lord and keep his Way.</p>
            <p>AND as to many of them, we may obſerve, with what admirable <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> they endured greater Trials, ſharper Pains, and longer Exerciſes, without Murmuring, and without Fainting, than ever yet we have known. How Diligent, Heavenly and Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful were ſome of them, under leſs Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and Help than we? The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Poor may ſhame many of the Rich: The Examples of ſome
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105563:30"/>young Converts, may ſhame Old Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: Religious Children may ſhame many Parents. There are younger Brethren, by whom the Elder are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone. Such who were new-born but lately, who exceed them that were in Chriſt many years before.</p>
            <p>HAD not they, whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> you are exhorted to <hi>follow,</hi> the like Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations as you meet with? Have not you the ſame Rule to walk by, the ſame Promiſes, Aſſiſtances and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements in the way to Heaven? Are your Wants to be ſupplied, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes to be cured, Difficulties to be conquered, Burdens to be endured, more, or greater, or other, than what they met with? And was not Death the Paſſage to Glory, as to all of them, and ſometimes by Lingering, Painful Sickneſs, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent to dying? Therefore you may, and ſhould take Heart by their Examples, and follow their Faith.</p>
            <p>HOW you ſhould do ſo, I will ſum
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105563:30"/>up in
<note place="bottom">* See Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Life of Faith, 4<hi>to.</hi> Chap. XXII. <hi>p.</hi> 585. And Mr. <hi>D. B</hi>'s Chriſtian Commemoration and Imitation of Saints Deported. 120. 1691. Where theſe things are more fully expreſs'd.</note> better Words than my own. <q>Let us fix upon the ſame Ends, to Glorifie God and Enjoy him; let us chooſe the ſame Guide and Captain of our Salvation, let us believe the ſame Goſpel, and build upon the ſame Promiſes, let us obey and truſt to the ſame Spirit of Holineſs and Comfort; let us live upon the ſame Truths, and exerciſe the ſame Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and watch againſt the ſame Sins and Corruptions; let us chooſe, prefer and uſe, the ſame Company, and other helps and means of Grace, and under all the Trials and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of this Life, act the ſame Faith, and Patience, and Hope unto the End; and we ſhall finiſh our Courſe as they did, and inherit the Promiſes as they do.</q> In order whereto,</p>
            <p n="3">III. LET us conſider <hi>the End of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105563:31"/>their Converſation.</hi> Be mindful of your Deceaſed Miniſters, that you may obſerve the happy End of their Converſation, and ſo be aſſiſted to follow their Faith. Their <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and Courſe of Life was agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their <hi>Faith,</hi> agreeable to the Doctrine they believed and taught, and their <hi>End</hi> was anſwerable: They lived in the Faith, and they dyed in the Faith, <hi>The End of their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> an End attended with Victory and Deliverance, the ſame Word that is uſed for <hi>Eſcape,</hi> 1 Cor. X. 13. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what Difficulties they met with, and yet did overcome; their Faith did not fail, their Hope did not periſh, their Courage did not faint. They en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured to the End, and finiſhed their Courſe, came off with Victory, and are got ſafe to Everlaſting Reſt.</p>
            <p>THE Conſideration of this, their happy End, knowing what they were, and what we are, ſhould encourage us to Follow them. It ought to raiſe our Deſires and Hopes, fix our Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105563:31"/>anſwer our Doubts, ſcatter our Fears, make Death leſs formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and the thoughts of Heaven more familiar, and ſo excite and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our Preparations for it: That following their Faith, we may with them at laſt receive the End of our Faith and Hope, the Salvation of our Souls.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I NOW come to the other Part of my Subject, to ſpeak of <hi>Your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Paſtor.</hi> Not that I deſign to give you the Hiſtory of his Parentage, Birth and Education, before he came to <hi>London,</hi> that is, before my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, or yours; but ſome Account of <hi>his Example, as a Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>as a Miniſter of Chriſt;</hi> that being the more ſenſible of your Loſs, you may take the more care to improve it.</p>
               <p>AND tho' I feel my ſelf a real and hearty Mourner with you, as for one whom I highly eſteemed and loved,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105563:32"/>and had a great deal of Reaſon to do ſo; I ſhall yet take care, that my Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection may not prompt me to ſay any thing concerning him, that cannot be well atteſted, either by my own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or by ſome of you who now hear me: As knowing that I ought not to ſpeak any thing that is not true, of a dead Friend, any more than raiſe an Evil Report of a living Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. But I ſpeak to thoſe, who knew his Doctrine and manner of Life, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, Faith, Patience, Love, Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering and Charity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. HE was, (conſidered <hi>as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) a lively Inſtance of inward God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Real Religion. He believed and practis'd what he preached to others. He lived in the firm Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Expectation of the Inviſible, Everlaſting World, and in diligent Preparation of himſelf and others for it. <hi>Humility,</hi> the Badge of our Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſt, was his Cloathing and Ornament, endeavouring to approve himſelf to God, and to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105563:32"/>of Men, as in the ſight of God, <hi>Not as pleaſing Men, but God who ſeeth the Heart,</hi> 2 Cor. X. 14, 15.</p>
               <p>PRAYER was his Delight, Strength and Excellency. I have hardly heard of any more abundant in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, more Conſtant and Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in it, with the like Variety, and Fervour upon all Occaſions. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what you had the Aſſiſtance of in Publick, in his Family and Cloſet every day, and alſo with his Wife, with that Seriouſneſs and Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency, that 'twould be thought incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, ſhould I name Particulars. And many times early in the morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day, after the Example of his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Maſter, he wreſtled with God in Secret Prayer. He taſted the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and reaped the Benefit of ſuch Converſe with God.</p>
               <p>AT other times, the <hi>Thought</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> (and how often in a day did he think of <hi>God!</hi>) and the very <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> was wont to ſtrike him with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105563:33"/>A we and Reverence. His whole Life was almoſt a Life of <hi>Prayer,</hi> which made his Face to ſhine, and his Grace to thrive, and gained him ſo much of the Divine Preſence in his publick Work, that ſometimes you might ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly diſcern that God was with him. He never went about to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe nor preach <hi>a Sermon,</hi> without moſt ſerious, earneſt <hi>Prayer</hi> before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, with a particular Reference to that Occaſion. He gave himſelf <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to Prayer,</hi> as well as to the Miniſtry of the Word. Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt and beſt of his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Learning he got upon his Knees.</p>
               <p>PRAISE and Thankfulneſs to God for all his Mercies, was a great part of his daily Prayer, and made up much of his Religion. The Love of God, and the joyful Praiſes of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, were his conſtant and moſt hearty Service. They that knew him beſt, can witneſs how much he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in <hi>Singing</hi> the Praiſes of God,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105563:33"/>and how ſtated a part of Family-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip he made it every day.</p>
               <p>THE Hely Scriptures were his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual, Delightful Study, as a Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Divine Wiſdom and Knowledge. He deſpiſed all Books of other Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in compariſon of this: And next to the Bible, he moſt eſteemed ſuch Practical Books, as Mr. <hi>R.</hi> and <hi>Joſ. Allen</hi>'s, and Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi>'s <hi>Kingdom of God amongſt Men,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>THE <hi>Lords-Day</hi> was his Peculiar Delight, and the Solemn Worſhip of it the Joy of his Soul: He was <hi>then</hi> and <hi>thereby</hi> revived, tho' he had been ill all the Week before: And when confined to his Chamber, by Pain and Languiſhing Sickneſs, (ſo as he could not attend the publick Aſſemblies,) how would he lament, the ſlight Sabbaths he thought he kept, and made Others keep? but could add, Thanks be to God, it was <hi>otherwiſe</hi> formerly.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105563:34"/>
               <p>HIS <hi>Relative Religion</hi> in his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, was moſt ſtrictly Chriſtian, and Exemplary. His Affection to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, evidenced in his Concern for their Souls, and particular Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of their Caſe to God, by Prayer, upon all Occaſions, aggravates their Loſs in his Death, but will make his Memory precious with them.</p>
               <p>AS to his Carriage and Behaviour abroad, he thought the Life of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, in ſome reſpects, was ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, if it were not <hi>Exemplary,</hi> and managed with greater Strictneſs, than that of Ordinary Chriſtians. What a Guard did he keep upon the Door of his Lips! how watchful was he over his Words! how ſhie of ordinary and common Converſation, upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, becauſe he could meet with ſo little ſerious and profitable Diſcourſe, even amongſt Thoſe, of whom it might have been expected! With what Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Faithfulneſs would he often begin ſuch Diſcourſe, as became a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105563:34"/>Miniſter, and a Chtiſtian? ſuitable to the Circumſtances and Conditions of thoſe he converſed with? And where there was Occaſion for it, with like Wiſdom and Fidelity, would he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh and reprove, to the hazard, ſometimes of loſing their Friendſhip, whom otherwiſe he had reaſon to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. But he knew, how to be ſevere againſt the Sin, and not diſcredit and expoſe the Sinner; he knew how to ſearch the Conſcience, and yet ſo far ſpare the perſon, as not to exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and provoke the Spirit.</p>
               <p>WHEN ſome time ſince I viſited, and prayed with him, (which I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I did no oftner,) enquiring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the State of his Soul, with Relation to God, and the other World: Whether all were well and calm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; he told me, that through the Grace of God, he could appeal to Him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Integrity; that he hoped, <hi>He had found mercy to be Faithful.</hi> Thro' the whole of his long Sickneſs, he had no Diſcouraging Fears, but
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105563:35"/>a ſerious, ſteady Truſt, and a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Hope in God, through the Merits of his Saviour, without <hi>high</hi> and <hi>full Aſſurance; which,</hi> he ſaid, was not ordinarily to be expected here, where Grace is ſo Imperfect. And yet ſometimes he hath experienc'd Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Conſolations. He hath been ſound alone, all in Tears; when upon Inquiry, what it was that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him, and made him ſad, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, he was very far from Grief: It was not Sorrow that made him weep, it was from Abundance of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Joy.</p>
               <p>HE often prayed for more <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> deſiring that <hi>Patience</hi> might continue, and <hi>have its perfect Work.</hi> And God granted it: For he had a calm, compoſed Spirit, under very long languiſhing, and ſome painful Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: He ſubmitted to the hand of God in all, without murmuring. And when every Body about him ſeemed greatly concerned, he himſelf was not.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105563:35"/>Conſider <hi>his Patience,</hi> you that were Eye-witneſſes of it; and <hi>Take my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Prophets, who have ſpoken to you in the Name of the Lord, for an Example</hi> of ſuffering Affliction, and of Patience.</p>
               <p>HIS ſerious Piety, was crowned with <hi>an Extenſive Charity.</hi> Beſides his Charity in Relieving the Poor, (in order to which he made Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to lay aſide a fit Proportion, of whatever the Providence of God allowed him; and that as ſoon as he received it, which he never after looked upon as his own:) Beſides that ſort of <hi>Charity,</hi> he was in Principle and Practice, very Charitable, to thoſe from whom he differed in Opinion. He loved All Men, in whom he could diſcern any thing of real Goodneſs. He did not confine the Church of Chriſt to <hi>a Party,</hi> or endeavour to make Proſelytes to <hi>Any:</hi> For he was of <hi>none,</hi> but <hi>that</hi> with all Chriſtians, for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> againſt the <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:105563:36"/>
               <p>HE did not think it the Excellency of <hi>Zeal,</hi> to go further than needs, from thoſe he did not fully agree with. He uſed the Lord's Prayer in Publick, and once a day in his Family, and thought he did his Duty therein. He had a <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>Truth,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> for <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Good Works:</hi> He remember'd that his Maſter was the Prince of <hi>Peace,</hi> and his Meſſage the Goſpel of <hi>Peace,</hi> that his Office was to be a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Peace,</hi> and that we are to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after <hi>Peace</hi> as well as Holineſs, and that <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers.</hi> He was ſenſible how much the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Real Religion is weakened, when the Bond of <hi>Peace</hi> is broken; and that when we bite and devour one another, we are in danger to be conſumed one of another. He was therefore an Enemy to Cenſorious Heats and Bitterneſs, and all ſuch Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Principles as deſtroy Love. He was of a truly Healing and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Spirit. I wiſh he may be <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105563:36"/>in theſe things, by all who knew him.</p>
               <p>I MENTION theſe Particulars, the rather, concerning <hi>his Perſonal Piety,</hi> to confute the Cavils of thoſe, who would run down all <hi>the younger Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> in groſs, as more looſe than their Predeceſſors. This is an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Devil, to hinder their Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; but the Foundation of it, I am perſwaded, is either <hi>Miſtake</hi> or <hi>Calumny.</hi> For what if one or two Candidates for the Miniſtry, be now and then heard of, who are taken in the Snare of the Devil, and fall from Hopeful Beginnings, ſo as to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Profeſſion, or quit it; ſhall the reſt, who are Humble, Sober, Diligent, and Serious, be leſs eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Was there ever in any Age, any ſort of Calling, or Profeſſion of Men in the World, whereof there may not be <hi>Some</hi> found, who are a Reproach and Blemiſh to the reſt? Would it not be very unjuſt, that <hi>Elder Miniſters,</hi> who are Wiſe and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105563:37"/>Learned, Upright and Exemplary, ſhould loſe the Reverence and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that is due to them, if there ſhould happen to be ſome Few of their Age and Standing, who come ſhort of ſuch Qualifications? I do here moſt heartily thank God, and Rejoice in Hope, as to the riſing Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, that I know many, (and hear of more,) of <hi>the younger Miniſters,</hi> who are well qualified for their Work, by improving, growing <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and reſolved Induſtry after <hi>more;</hi> with deep Seriouſneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity towards God: And therefore will deſerve the Eſteem and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all that know them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. LET me now Conſider him as <hi>a Miniſter of Chriſt.</hi> He was apt, and ready to Teach, fit for Publick Service, and Succeſsful in it. How much did he anſwer the Apoſtle's Character, <q>To be Blameleſs, as a Steward of God, not ſelf-will'd, not ſoon angry, not given to Wine, not Contentious, not given to filthy
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105563:37"/>Luce; a lover of Hoſpitality, a lover of good men; ſober, juſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, temperate, holding faſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Word, as he had been taught; able, by ſound Doctrine, to exhort, and to convince Gain ſayers; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it his buſineſs to ſave himſelf, and them that heard him,</q> 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> VII. 8, 9. His Heart was in his Work, and he wholly gave himſelf to it. He did not ſeek great things to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: The Honour of Chriſt, and the Salvation of Souls, was what he aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, and longed for, and laboured for.</p>
               <p>AND ſuch was his unwearied <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> in the well Improvement of his Time, that he quickly grew Rich in all Spiritual Giſts, by the Bleſſing of God on the diligent hand: And from time to time he increaſed conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably. He found it true, That <hi>to him that hath,</hi> and uſeth well what he hath, <hi>to him ſhall be given, and he ſhall have more abundantly.</hi> He knew the Weight of the Miniſterial Work,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105563:38"/>to watch for the Flock, to ſtrengthen the Weak, to confirm the Strong, to ſatisfie the Doubtful, to reſolve the Scrupulous, to anſwer Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And who is ſufficient for theſe things, without a great deal of Induſtry, in hope of Divine Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? He knew the Difficulty of his Work, to evidence Truth to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to awaken Sinners to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and then to manifeſt Chriſt the Redeemer, and Saviour of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; to Reprove ſome with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and others with Sharpneſs; to pour Balm into Wounded Spirits, and to ſpeak a Word in ſeaſon to the Wearied Soul; to difference the Sheep from the Goats, the Precious from the Vile, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to manage all this with a deep ſenſe of the Worth of <hi>Souls,</hi> and the ineſtimable Price where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were purchaſed, and the Aweful Account that he muſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after give to the Great Shepherd. The Conſideration of theſe things, made him Diligent, and reſolved, and unwearied in what he undertook, ſo long as he was Able.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105563:38"/>
               <p>THO' he were as well able, as moſt, with very little Preparation, to ſpeak pertinently and uſefully upon any Subject; yet he made Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not to give to God that which coſt him nothing. He would not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that in publick, which he had not conſidered, and digeſted, and prayed over. He durſt not preſume, in the Name of Chriſt, to vent raw and indigeſted Notions, which he had not well thought of; or to entertain his Hearers, with any looſe and ramb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Thoughts, that came next into his Head.</p>
               <p>AS to his <hi>Style,</hi> he was not for an affected Strain of Words; yet far from taking any ſuch Liberty, as argued Indiſcretion, or expoſed to Contempt. He hath given ſufficient Proof, upon ſeveral Occaſions, that he was Maſter of the beſt Language, whenever he pleaſed to make uſe of it; but had the Wiſdom, to ſuit his Words, as well as Matter, ſo as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105563:39"/>might beſt anſwer the End, of doing Good to thoſe to whom he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>YOU know very well, that <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> was that part of his Work, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Heart was more eſpecially en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged: And that he durſt not ſpeak to ſecure, drowſie Sinners, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt, Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> in a cold and careleſs manner. He knew the weightieſt Matter, without lively Application to enforce it, is but like Bullet without Powder. With what tender Affection, would he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite Sinners to Chriſt? With what moving Expoſtulations, would he addreſs himſelf to all ſorts? In fuitable Expreſſions to Young and Old! With Clearneſs he would Open, and Apply the Doctrinal Articles of Religion, and, by Catechiſing, inſtruct the Ignorant. With Strength and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Arguments, he enforced the Duties of Chriſtian Practice. And how readily did he embrace all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing good in this
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105563:39"/>kind, to the utmoſt of his Strength, and beyond it?</p>
               <p>HE would often uſe the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle, <hi>I am not ſent to baptize,</hi> comparatively, <hi>but to preach the Goſpel,</hi> which is the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God to the Salvation of the Soul. Not that he neglected the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments: For, beſides <hi>the Lord's Supper,</hi> which he adminiſtred every Month, he had great Succeſs in bringing many Adult Perſons to be Baptized, in the publick Congregation, ſometimes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral in one day.</p>
               <p>HE was careful to follow his Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Teaching, with Private Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Viſits, eſpecially of the Sick; ſo far as his Relation to ſo many, and bodily weakneſs would permit. With Tenderneſs would he apply Comfort to the Mourners in <hi>Sion.</hi> He was skilful in binding up the Broken in Heart. Many reſorted to him upon that Account. And with Compaſſion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105563:40"/>and Gentleneſs he would deal with Offenders, in order to their Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. How earneſtly did he deſire, and ſeek, the Peace, and Holineſs of his People? His very Soul was grieved, if he heard of any of them, walking diſorderly. He could ſay, with the Apoſtle, <hi>I have you in my heart, and God is witneſs, how greatly I long after you all, in the Bowels of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Phil. 7.8.</p>
               <p>YOU Remember, concerning his <hi>Preaching,</hi> how <hi>practically</hi> both for Matter and Manner, he inſiſted on the Great Things of Religion: He did not amuſe his Hearers, (whom he conſidered, as near the Grave and the Eternal World,) with <hi>Controverſies,</hi> which they need not underſtand; and concerning which, Wiſe and Good Men may have different Sentiments, and yet be <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and bear with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>He carefully avoided <hi>Extrems,</hi> in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105563:40"/>opening and applying the Truths of the Goſpel. He was wont to exhort Men, to work out their Salvation with all Diligence, and to ſtrive to the utmoſt, to enter into Heaven; and yet after all, to truſt and relye <hi>only</hi> on the Mediation and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt. He preach'd, and prov'd, the Neceſſity of an <hi>Imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and yet urg'd the neceſſity of an <hi>Inherent One.</hi> That the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt, and his Sacrifice for Sin, might be honoured, and yet the Holy Ghoſt, in his ſanctifying Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, may be honoured too. He did not make Morality the whole Duty of Man; nor yet deceive the People, by ſaying, that Chriſt repented for them, and Believed for them. He magnified the <hi>Special Grace</hi> of God, in the Converſion of a Sinner, and yet preached <hi>Repentance towards God,</hi> as neceſſary to Forgiveneſs, with <hi>Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Without cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly determining which is <hi>firſt,</hi> when <hi>both</hi> are needful, and never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. He laid the whole ſtreſs of our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105563:41"/>Salvation on Jeſus Chriſt. He aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the Beginning, Progreſs, and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of all Spiritual Good, entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Free-grace of God. And yet the Impenitence, Unbelief and Damnation of Sinners, he juſtly charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on their own Wilfulneſs, in hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Devil. And if this be <hi>Legal Preaching,</hi> what is it to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>ACCORDINGLY we find, that God honoured him with great Succeſs. He had Eminent Seals of his Miniſtry, at his firſt Beginning, and many more afterwards: <hi>He was a good Man, and full of the Holy Ghoſt and Faith, and much People were added to the Lord.</hi> There are many of you, who bleſs God, that you ever ſaw or heard him. You are his Witneſſes, that he did not run in vain, nor labour in vain. His Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was made effectual to the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many. His Tong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was a Tree of Life unto many: You will be his Crown of Rejoycing, in the day of the Lord. And if they that be wiſe, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ine
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105563:41"/>as the brightneſs of the Firmament; and <hi>They that turn many to Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever,</hi> Dan. XII. 3. We may believe, he will have a proportionable Reward.</p>
               <p>HIS extraordinary Application to his Work, and Diligence in it, (which haſtened his Death,) may increaſe his Glory. Tho' ſome make a Queſtion, whether a Miniſter, who Converts ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls here; or another, that is as faithful and diligent, and yet hath not ſuch Succeſs; Which of theſe ſhall have the moſt Glory in Heaven. Some think the Second, becauſe the one had much Encouragement and Comfort here, which the other had not, for want of Succeſs; and yet might ſay, <hi>Tho' I have laboured in vain, and ſpent my ſtrength for nought; yet ſurely my Judgment is with the Lord, and my Work with my God.</hi> I ſhall not loſe my Labour, <hi>Iſa.</hi> XLIX. 4. And as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>We are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, a ſweet Savour of Chriſt, in them that are ſaved, and in them that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105563:42"/>periſh.</hi> 'Tis certain he bare you much upon his Heart, in daily Prayer, in order to the Succeſs of his Miniſtry among you: And gave Thanks to God for any ſuch Fruit, for any Service he had been enabled to do for your Souls. And was affected with your grateful Senſe of it, teſtified by your Kindneſs to him, in his laſt Sickneſs, which he thankfully acknowledged.</p>
               <p>SOME of you will never forget the <hi>Laſt Sermon</hi> he preached in Publick, when with much Difficulty he was brought into the Pulpit, how he ſpake as in the View and Senſe of another World, with what ſerious Affection he prov'd and preſs'd the Obligation we are under, <hi>Whether we live, that we live to the Lord; or whether we dye, that we dye to the Lord;</hi> ſo that, <hi>Whether we live or dye, we are the Lords,</hi> Rom. XIV. 8. and that if we be thought <hi>beſides our ſelves,</hi> or <hi>ſober,</hi> it is for your ſakes. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> V. 13. How agreeable to the Senſe of his Heart, was it for him, from ſuch a paſſage to ſay, <q>Let
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105563:42"/>me be eſteemed a Fool, or a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and beſides my ſelf, if I may but gain <hi>One Soul;</hi> let the Devil roar againſt me, if I can but ſnatch the Prey out of his Jaws; let him calumniate and revile me, if I can but weaken his Kingdom.</q> But when by ſuch an Eſſay, he was made ſenſible of his own Weakneſs, and found himſelf really diſabled for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service, he then declared he was ſatisfied; <hi>Now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I know my Work is done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IF any of you are ready to Object, that his Work might not have been done ſo ſoon, if he had prudently managed his Health and Strength, and not ſhortned his Days by <hi>Over-doing.</hi> I grant, that his Zeal and Fervour, and unwearied Diligence, tho' from a good Principle, might, as to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Proſpect, have been managed ſo, as to continue his Uſefulneſs lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But let us take heed, not to blame him too much for Imprudence in this matter, unleſs we are certain,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105563:43"/>that we know what it is to long for the Salvation of Souls, to be filled with Love to Chriſt, and to live above the Love of Life, at the rate he did. However,
<note place="bottom">* Dr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> of Temptation. 4<hi>to.</hi> Part. III. Chap. 15.</note> it may be reckoned as one of <hi>Satan's Temptations,</hi> to the moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and uſeful Miniſters, by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, to lay a Snare for their Lives; laviſhing their Strength, in a Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality of Pains, for the good of Souls, which, like a Thief in a Candle, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately waſts them; whereas a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter husbanded Strength might be more advantagious, by continuing the Light longer: And yet their Ends are ſo ſincere, their Work ſo pleaſant, and their Hearts ſo enflamed with Zeal, that they ſeldom obſerve, as they might, that the Devil is glad of the Opportunity, to deſtroy them with their own Weapon.</p>
               <p>THIS many of his Freinds took Notice of; among others, that Great and Good Man, Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105563:43"/>much eſteemed and loved him, (not long before he left this World,) he ſent him this kind Meſſage, That he ſhould take heed, <hi>leſt he ſpent too faſt.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> loved him, I reckon to his Honour: He was one of many, who thank'd God for the Aſſiſtance he received, as a Chriſtian, and as a Miniſter, from the uſeful Books, Preaching, and Converſation of that Excellent Man: I freely concur with him therein, having reaſon to thank God upon the like Account.</p>
               <p>HE was Fervent in Spirit, ſerving the Lord: His own Soul was fill'd with Zeal, to kindle Holy Fire in the Souls of others. He was willing to ſpend, and to be ſpent: And hereby he waſted, and at laſt conſumed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. He ran faſt, and was the ſooner at his Journies-End. But if we judge of our Days and Time on Earth, by the good we do in this World, and the Progreſs we make in preparing for another; that is, if we judge by weight, and not by meaſure; <hi>He
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105563:44"/>lived long, he dyed old,</hi> and <hi>full of days.</hi> Many a Man with a grey Head, had not lived ſo much, tho' he might have been longer in the World: For he lived more in a Year, than many do in ſeven. He did more Service in leſs than <hi>Thirty three Years,</hi> than many do in <hi>Threeſcore.</hi> Tho' we reckon God took him off in the midſt of his Days, and in the midſt of his Miniſtry; it was not too ſoon for Him, tho' it may be for you. He was ripe and ready.</p>
               <p>And conſidering his long languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pains and Weakneſs, (under all the Attempts and Endeavours for his Recovery, which Humane Art, Skill and Care, with the Earneſt Prayers of many for Succeſs, could contribute:) We may ſay, that God was kind and Gracious to call him home. He did not ſo properly take away his Life, as
<note place="bottom">* <hi>Non tam ereptam ei vitam a Dijs Immortalibus, ſed Donatam Mertem.</hi> Cicero <hi>concerning</hi> Craſſus.</note> 
                  <hi>beſtow Death.</hi> Or to uſe the Words of
<note place="bottom">† Dr. <hi>Sam. Anneſly,</hi> concerning Dr. <hi>Drake.</hi>
                  </note> an Eminent, Elder Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105563:44"/>who went to Heaven the ſame day, (<hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> an Aged <hi>Paul,</hi> and a Young <hi>Timothy,</hi> within few hours) who ſpeaking of Another on the like Occaſion, ſaith, <hi>That he went out like one of the Lamps of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, with a ſweet perfume:</hi> So hath my Dear Brother left this World, and left a Good Name, as of a pretious, ſweet ſmelling Odour, behind him.</p>
               <p>AND now <hi>He is gone,</hi> ſhould I ſay any thing further to <hi>Surviving Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and to you that ſate under his Miniſtry; I ſhall but open another Sluice of Sorrow. If I ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him as <hi>a Husband,</hi> I might ſpeak to Her, who ſo carefully and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſiſted him in his long <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> and beſeech her to Remember, how he was the Guide of her Youth; to Remember his Love to her Perſon, and his Love to her Soul, and beg of God, that ſhe may experience the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Bleſſing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> LIV. 5. <hi>Thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker is thine Husband, the Lord of Hoſts is his Name, and thy Redeemer
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105563:45"/>the Holy One of Iſrael, the God of the Whole Earth ſhall he be called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>FOR <hi>his Children,</hi> who may yet be more profited by our Prayers, than Counſel; let us pray to God, that as their Father's Memory is Bleſſed, his Poſterity after him may be ſo. And we may do this with the more Hope, becauſe there is the Entail of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Mercy, to be pleaded from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to Generation, both on the <hi>Father's</hi> Side, and on <hi>the Mother's;</hi> as being both deſcended from <hi>Excellent Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Eminent Miniſters.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Accounts, you are encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to truſt God, as to <hi>the Children.</hi> Hoping that their Father's God, and their Grand Fathers God, will be <hi>their God,</hi> and <hi>Guide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>SHOULD I conſider him as <hi>a Son,</hi> as <hi>a Brother,</hi> as <hi>a Kinſman,</hi> as <hi>a Friend,</hi> &amp;c. and how he carried it in each Relation, I muſt be very large. You are ſenſible of your Loſs, be thankful to God for him. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105563:45"/>his Example, follow his Faith, think of him with Pleaſure, and not with Grief; not as loſt, but as deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and crowned, and at Reſt in Everlaſting Joy.</p>
               <p>TO <hi>You</hi> who attended his Miniſtry, and ſhall behold him no more in the Land of the Living, nor ever hear him more in this, or any other Pulpit; let me add a few Words; <hi>Remember him who hath ſpoken to you the Word of God.</hi> Eſpecially be careful to practice the Sermons, you have heard him preach, and ſeen him live: Imitate whatſoever you ſaw of the Image and Life of Chriſt in him; and write down any thing that was very remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, that you ever heard from him in Publick or Private; any thing that did particularly affect you, or may be of Service to you.</p>
               <p>YOU have been favoured with a Succeſſion of ſuch Burning and Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Lights, as are not ſet up in every Candle-ſtick. Remember the Sound
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105563:46"/>Inſtructions, the Faithful Warnings, the Earneſt Exhortations, the Fervent Labours, and Exemplary Lives of your Deceaſed Guides. What Fruit may God expect from you, after ſuch a Seeds-time as you have had! Your laſt Miniſter had a Lean, Withered, Waſted, Conſumed Body, that you might be fat and flouriſhing in the Courts of the Lord.</p>
               <p>BUT <hi>You</hi> are of <hi>two Sorts:</hi> Either you have profited by his Miniſtry, or not. If the former, you have reaſon to be thankful to God. You that have been convinced, and awakened by his Preaching, that have been touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Heart under his Miniſtry, who have often gone away ſtriking of your Breaſts, and with Weeping Eyes driven to your Knees, when you came home, and obliged to come to him again, ſaying, <hi>Sir, what muſt I do to be ſaved? You</hi> cannot but feel and lament this Loſs. Your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Tears are his Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And of ſeveral of you he might
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105563:46"/>ſay, with the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Tho' you have ten thouſand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers in Chriſt, ye have not many Fathers; for in Chriſt Jeſus I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten you by the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. IV. 15. To the like purpoſe I might ſpeak to <hi>Others,</hi> who have by his Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, been built up in their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith, confirmed, ſtrengthened, encouraged, eſtabliſhed and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>THERE is another Sort, who reap'd no ſuch Advantage by him. His Death is a ſharp Reproof to ſuch. How far unprofitable Hearers may be guilty of the Death of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as well as an Unfaithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Blood of Souls, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Conſideration. With how many did he prevail, but could not with you! He ſhall now be a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to you no more. Be perſwaded to look back, and think with your ſelves, what earneſt Entreaties he uſed with you, in the Name of Chriſt, beſeeching you to be reconciled to God.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105563:47"/>How he longed for your Salvation: How he ſtudied, and prayed, and waited for Succeſs. Be not deceiv'd, not a Sermon he ever preached, or a Conviction you ever had under his Preaching, but muſt be accounted for. Tho' the Man be dead, and the Miniſter be dead; yet his Meſſage doth not dye, and ſhall not fall to the Ground. Tho' all Fleſh be Graſs, and the Glory of it as the Flower of the Field, yet <hi>The Word of the Lord abideth for ever,</hi> and not a Tittle of it ſhall be unaccompliſhed.</p>
               <p>IT will be ſad indeed, if he that ſpent his Health, and Strength, and Life, for you, ſhould be obliged at laſt to Witneſs againſt you, and to ſay, (tho' not with ſuch compaſſionate Words and Tears as formerly,) <q>
                     <hi>Lord,</hi> I did Inſtruct, Admoniſh, and Exhort them, in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon; but could not perſwade them to leave their ſins, and come to Chriſt, that they might have Life. I told them of the Danger of their preſent
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105563:47"/>State, and what was like to be the End of it. I told them plainly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again, that <hi>now only</hi> was the time to be reconciled to God; I opened to them the Goſpel-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and ſhewed them the Riches of God's Grace in Chriſt, and his Readineſs, and Sufficiency to ſave the chiefeſt of Sinners, and that his Blood cleanſeth from all ſin. But they would not conſider, they would not regard, they would dye!</q> O with what concerned, and awakened Souls, ſhould <hi>We Miniſters</hi> ſtudy, preach and pray, when every Sermon, for ought we know, may witneſs againſt Some of thoſe that hear it, in the day of Reckoning! O pity Us, and therein your Selves! for <hi>We do not deſire the woful day, Lord, thou knoweſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>WHAT would you have us ſay
<note place="bottom">* See more to this purpoſe, in Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s. <hi>Sermon of Judgment.</hi> 8vo. <hi>p.</hi> 30, 34.</note>, in the Day of Judgment, if God ſhould ask us? Did you tell this Sinner of his need of Chriſt, of the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105563:48"/>Miſery of his Natural, Sinful State, of the Glory of the World to come, of the Vanity of this <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Should we lye, and ſay, we did not? We muſt unavoidably bear Witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and ſay; Lord, we did what we could, according to our weak Abilities, to reclaim them: Indeed our own Thoughts of Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Things were ſo low, and our Hearts ſo dull, that we muſt confeſs we did not follow them ſo cloſe, nor ſpeak ſo earneſtly as we ſhould have done: We did not cry ſo loud, or lift up our Voice as a Trumpet to awaken them, (<hi>Iſa,</hi> 58.1.) We confeſs we did not ſpeak to them with ſuch melting Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and with ſuch Streams of Tears beſeech them to regard, as a Matter of ſuch great Concernment ſhould have been ſpoken with; we did not fall on our Knees to them, and ſo earneſtly beg of them for the Lord's ſake, to have Mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own Souls, as we ſhould have done. But yet we told them
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:105563:48"/>the Meſſage of God, and we ſtudied to ſpeak it to them, as plainly and as piercingly as we could. Fain we would have convinced them of their Sin and Miſery, but we could not: Fain we would have drawn them to the admiration of Chriſt, but they made light of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.5. We would fain have brought them to the Contempt of this vain World, and to ſet their mind on the World to come, but we could not: Some Compaſſion, thou knoweſt Lord, we had to their Souls, many a Weeping or Groaning Hour we have had in ſecret; becauſe they would not hear and obey; and ſome ſad Complaints we have made over them in publick: We told them, that they muſt ſhortly dye, and come to Judgment; and that this World would deceive them, and have them in the duſt: We told them, that the Time was at hand, when nothing but Chriſt will do them good, and nothing but the Favour of God would be ſufficient for their Happineſs: But we could never get them to lay
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105563:49"/>it to Heart. Many a time did we entreat them to think ſoberly of this Life, and the Life to come, and to compare them together, with the Faith of Chriſtians, and the Reaſon of Men, but they would not do it. Many a time did we entreat them, but to take now and then an hour in ſecret, to conſider, <hi>Who</hi> made them, and <hi>for what</hi> he had made them, and why they were ſent into this World; and what there Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here is, and <hi>Whether</hi> they are going, and how it will go with them at their latter End: But we could never get the moſt of them to ſpend one hour in ſerious thoughts of theſe weighty Matters. Many a time did we entreat them to try, whether they were Regenerate or not; whether Chriſt and his Spirit were in them, or not; whether their Souls were brought back to God by Sanctification; but they would not try: We did beſeech them to make ſure Work, and not leave ſuch a Matter as Everlaſting
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:105563:49"/>Joy or Torment, to a bold and mad Adventure; but we could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail. We entreated them to lay all other Buſineſſes aſide a little while in the World, and to enquire by the Direction of the Word of God, what would become of them in the World to come; and to judge themſelves before God came to judge them, ſeeing they had the Law and Rule of Judgment before them: But their Minds were blinded, and their Hearts were hardned, and the Profit, and Pleaſure, and Honour of this World, did either ſtop their Ears, or quickly ſteal away their Hearts, ſo that we could never get them to a ſober Conſideration, nor ever win their Hearts to God.</p>
                  <p>This will be the <hi>Witneſs,</hi> that many hundred Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel muſt give in againſt the Souls of their People at that day.</p>
               </q>
               <p>But to draw to a Cloſe, Let us all be affected with his Death, ſo as
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105563:50"/>wiſely to improve it. The Removal of ſuch an one, at his Age, is <hi>a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Loſs;</hi> not only to his Family, and to the Congregation; but to the Poor, to the City, to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to the Church of Chriſt. One of a clear Head, and warm Heart; who underſtood, believ'd and obey'd the Goſpel. One of a Peaceable, and Publick Spirit; Abundant in Prayer, and of an Exemplary Life, and of Extraordinary Diligence to do Good: Being fitted for it, as he was filled with Love to Chriſt, and the Souls of Men, to carry on the great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Faith and Holineſs, to the utmoſt of his Power, in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion God had put him: And full of Thoughts and Care therein to abide with God. But mourn <hi>not for Him.</hi> Some ſorrowful Concern, 'tis true, is unavoidable, if you are ſenſible of your Loſs; and 'tis alſo fit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming: For 'tis a Judgment upon any, and a Reproach upon <hi>a Miniſter,</hi> to dye unlamented: As if his Life were of no Uſe, and the World were
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:105563:50"/>weary of him. But you need not mourn <hi>for Him,</hi> when you Conſider Who he was, and Where he Now is, being exalted to a higher Sphere of Action and Enjoyment, for which through Grace and Holy Diligence he was prepared: And ſo for ever deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from all Pain and Sickneſs, from Sin and Sorrow, Corruption and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. If you follow his Faith and Patience, you ſhall meet him again, in Unutterable and Endleſs Joy.</p>
               <p>HEREUPON you will do well to admit the Thought, that all <hi>your other Miniſters</hi> are mortal and dying, and that <hi>you your Selves</hi> are ſo: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould improve their Lives and and Labours, as you ſhall wiſh you had done when <hi>They</hi> are Dead, or when <hi>You</hi> your ſelves are ready to dye.</p>
               <p>TO <hi>Conclude,</hi> Becauſe He alone who made this Breach, hath the Reſidue of the Spirit, and can ſupply it; let me adviſe you, tho' the Shepherd be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105563:51"/>ſmitten, yet that the Sheep do not ſcatter. Let not this Breach occaſion Others; but Agree together, and take the beſt Advice you can, in looking out ſpeedily for a <hi>Suitable Supply.</hi> And the Lord direct you to a Man after his own Heart, that may be like-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>my Deceaſed Brother.</hi> And whatever you have received, and heard, and learnt, and ſeen in Him, as a Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Chriſt, that do; and <hi>The God of Grace, and Peace, be with you.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:51"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for</hi> John Lawrence, <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in the</hi> Poultrey.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Life, publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> Folio.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lorimers</hi> Apology for the Miniſters that ſubſcribed to the ſtating the Truths and Errors in Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s Book, in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Trails</hi> Letter to a Miniſter in the Country. In 4<hi>o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lorimers</hi> Remarks on Mr. <hi>T. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi> Diſcourſe of the Goſpel, proving that the Goſpel-Covenant is a Law of Grace; anſwering his Objections to the contrary. In 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord-Mayor, <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1693. 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— his Thankſgiving Sermon, <hi>April</hi> 16. 1696. before the Lord Mayor. 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> Sermon of Juſtification, 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Slaters</hi> Thankſgiving Sermon, <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. 1692. 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— his Sermons at the Funerals of Mr. <hi>John Reynolds,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fincher,</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel, 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Burtons</hi> Diſcourſes of Purity, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Repentance, and ſeeking firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Pubiſhed with a Preface by Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> late Arch-biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Wilkins</hi>'s Diſcourſes of the Gift of Prayer and Preaching, the latter much Enlarged by the Biſhops of <hi>Norwich</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Samuel Slaters</hi> Earneſt Call to Family Religion, in Eighteen Sermons. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Help to true Spelling and Reading, or a very eaſie Method for Teaching Children, or elder Perſons, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Spell, and exactly to Read Engliſh, in much leſs time then uſual. By <hi>William Scoffin.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Addy</hi>'s <hi>Stenographia,</hi> or the Art of Short-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting compleated in a far more compendious way than any extant. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Addy</hi>'s Short-hand Bible in the ſame Character.</p>
            <p>Sir. <hi>Robert Howards</hi> Free Diſcourſe: Wherein the Doctrines which make for Tyranny are Diſplayed. The Title of our Rightful and Lawful King <hi>William</hi> vindicated, and the Unreaſonableneſs and Miſchievous Tendency of the Odious Diſtinction of a King <hi>de Facto</hi> and <hi>de Jure</hi> Diſcovered. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robinſons Cambridge</hi> Phraſes, being a General Phraſe-Book for the Uſe of Schools. In 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>London-Diſpenſatory</hi> reduced to the Practice of the <hi>London</hi> Phyſitians, wherein are contained the Medicines Gallenical and Chymical, that are now in Uſe, thoſe out of uſe omitted, and thoſe in uſe not in the latter Copy here added. By <hi>John Peachey,</hi> of the Colledge of Phyſitians, <hi>London.</hi> In 12<hi>o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dying Mans Aſſiſtant, or ſhort Inſtructions for thoſe who are concerned in the preparing of ſick Perſons for Death. Being alſo no leſs worthy the Conſideration of all good Chriſtians in Time of Health. As ſhewing the importance of an Early Preparation for their latter End; with Regard as well to their Temporal as Eternal State. 12<hi>o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Alkins</hi> Engliſh Grammar, or the Engliſh Tongue reduced to Grammatical Rules. Compoſed for the uſe of Schools. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105563:52"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
